okay let's move on and let's now discuss
more earnings gopal balachandran the CFO
and chief risk officer at ICS Alomar
General uh Insurance joins in on the
show right now gopal healthy premiums or
other health premiums in retail and
corporate category have gone up by 133%
and 34% from what I understand what are
the shifting trends that you are seeing
in health insurance space in this postco
environment I think that's a great
question to ask and given the EnV M that
all of us have gone through over the
last couple of years clearly health
insurance has possibly gained a lot more
prominence when you look at it from an
overall Market perspective uh which is
why whenever you see possibly in the
last couple of years during the peak of
covid times clearly the demand for
health insurance uh saw a significant
uptake uh particularly during the peak
of waves the growth in the health
insurance Market used to be upwards of
35 40% in that particular periods
whenever the waves had happened uh and
even as we speak I think demand Trend
continues to be quite robust I think
from an is Lombard standpoint I think
Health has always been an area of focus
whether it is Corporate health or for
the matter of fact even retail Health on
the retail Health space as we have been
kind of talking to the markets we have
been investing in expanding distribution
which is why if you see even as a part
of the uh uh press release that we put
out we have added almost close to about
1,100 people as we speak uh including
new hirings that we have been doing over
the last last 9month period in order to
expand distribution that has clearly
translated into let's say positive
outcome in terms of growth as you
rightly mentioned for us for example
when you look at the quarter one numbers
I'm giving you numbers for both health
and corporate put together the growth
for us has been almost about 33% this if
you look at Visa the market for the
market the growth in the health
insurance space has been 21% so both
segments have done well in the corporate
space I think again what we have been
speaking uh over the last last 9 to 12
months given the fact that we had seen
elevated levels of health insurance
claims we have been able to also get uh
price increases affected at the time of
renewal of our policies which again has
kind of augured well in terms of growth
in the corporate Health space and Retail
as I said given the fact that we have
been continuing on investing in
distribution I think the growth momentum
looks quite
solid Mr balachandran talk to us about
the overall Trends you seeing in claims
it's still around 70% when are you
expecting
normalization on motor insurance claim
definitely we are seeing increase in the
number of intimation consequent to
economic activities coming back to
normal on the health side again on the
retail Indemnity space uh what we had
seen clearly is again during covid waves
people are apprehensive to possibly get
some of their treatments done unless and
until it's a medical emergency which
cannot be avoidable but but um on in in
respect of normal health insurance
claims customers had chosen to possibly
elect to to postpone their treatment to
a later date now that's something that
we have seen a bunch up of cases coming
up in quarter one so again on the non-id
health insurance claims we have seen an
increase in the number of claim
intimations the question for us what you
rightly asked is there is it going to be
a pattern of continued increase in claim
intimation or is it more a bunch up of
cases that has happened in this
particular period is something that we
will have to wait out wait and watch out
for the next maybe I would say two to
three months post which we will be able
to get a sense of direction in terms of
how the health insurance non-id Health
claim intimations will Trend like so
that's one direction that we'll have to
wait and see the other thing what we
have seen equally during this period is
I mean when you go today for to any
Hospital you will clearly see a increase
in the number of procedures that a
customer has to undergo that
automatically results in maybe an
increase in the average claims cost and
now again the question for us is whether
this increase in the average claims cost
is uh is structural or is it more uh
temporary phenomenon so as I said
similar to the claim intimation on the
health insurance side this is something
that we will again watch out for over
the next maybe a quarter or so and see
whether the increase in the average
claim sizes is a trend line that is
likely to sustain or otherwise but
overall there is definitely an increase
in the number of claim intimations and
life insurers will soon be able to sell
the health insurance are you seeing the
market dynamics changing how will you
look at
competition so one at this point of time
it is at the proposal stage so honestly
we do not know in which shape and form
will that kind of take shape so
therefore we'll have to wait for further
guidelines and uh in further guidelines
from in the regulatory Authority so we
will wait and wait and see how it
develops having said that I think the
point that I made with respect to the
opportunity the health insurance space
is quite significant if you look at the
penetration on the health insurance base
um as I mentioned today what you
normally see as health insurance is only
hospitalization based Insurance
coverages two-thirds of the healthcare
spend is pretty much out of pocket which
is not necessarily covered through any
form of insurance as we speak that's a
great opportunity um if you look at even
for the set of customers who have taken
a health insurance cover there is a
clear question that comes up with
respect to adequacy of coverage because
that's what one realizes when a customer
ends up for an unfortunate reason at the
hospital he or she realizes that maybe
the Quantum of coverages coverage that
one has got either through the employ or
employee offering or an individual
taking a coverage on his her own uh
intent is proved to be inadequate so
therefore there's an opportunity for
upsell as well which clearly presents an
opportunity on the health insurance base
sure lastly uh you know when it comes to
pricing with higher inflation how is it
that you're seeing price readjustments
and how will you look to adjust over the
next year or
so on motor third party side what we
have seen as a part of the price
notification is a low single digit uh
price increase that has been affected on
the TP segment on motor own damage when
you look at the fact that I said that
there has been low claim insurances and
relatively new vehicle sales have also
been lowered now obviously that meant
heighten levels of competitive intensity
and motor as a segment always has been
uh competitive intensive resulting into
let's say for the overall industry on
the motor own damage side the combined
ratio is almost close to about 110 115%
so that doesn't become viable sense for
us to kind of operate at that levels of
combine which is why from an is Lombard
standpoint I think what we have been
doing towards not just now inherently
whenever we have seen highend levels of
competition we have tried to be a bit
cautious in so far as growth is
concerned and two in so far as affecting
a price change for example we started
affecting price increases from Q4 of
this year and it continues as we speak
in some of the select models and some of
the
select geographies where we kind of
operate at so that's been the trend
again a low single digit number is the
price increase that we have affected in
the motor own damage segment coming
quickly on the health I think this was
again a call that we took almost towards
quarter 3 of 2021 where we had kind of
affected uh a price increase on the
retail Health space after almost close
to four five years the price increase
that we had affected was close close to
about 8% but so that's how we kind of
continue to monitor the portfolio from
an Isis lombar standpoint we look at
different segments and see the claim
pattern and corresponding to which we
kind of look at uh pricing for the
segments appropriate